[SOUND] So
那么
we're used to seeing two-dimensional images, and
我们经常见到二维影像
we can use two-dimensional images to perceive our three-dimensional world, and
我们可以利用二维影像来认知三维世界
we perceive time as maybe a fourth dimension, but
时间也许可看成第四维
then our ability to perceive dimensions is limited to those three or four dimensions.
我们感知维度的能力也就局限在三维或者四维之中
Parallel coordinates offer us a way of plotting even higher dimensional
平行坐标系给我们提供了一种可以绘制
spaces than that.
比三 四维更高维度图像的方法
So in looking at the higher dimensional drawings or
所以在看更高维绘图或者
higher dimensional spaces, you can think of something like a square.
更高维度空间时 你可以想象一个正方形
A square consists of two one-dimensional lines,
正方形是由两条一维直线组成
these two vertical lines, that are separated horizontally.
这两条垂直的线 它们在水平方向被分开
I've taken a one dimensional line, copied into a second vertical line and
我将一条一维的线 复制出另一个垂直的线
then connected them up with lines between the vertices.
然后用线将两条线的两端进行连接
So I've now got a two-dimensional square.
这样我就得到了一个二维的正方形
If I want to make this two-dimensional square into a three-dimensional cube,
如果我想将这个二维正方形变成三维立方体
I just copy the square, and move it in a direction, and then I just link up
我只需要复制这个正方形 然后将它沿一方向移开
the corresponding vertices with lines, and that gives me a three-dimensional cube.
将两个正方形的顶点连接 于是我就得到了一个立方体
If I want a four-dimensional cube, I just take the three-dimensional cube and
如果你要得到一个四维的立方体
I make another copy of it and offset it in another direction, and
我只需复制这个三维的立方体 再将它沿另一方向移开
then just draw lines between the corresponding vertices and it gives me
然后再用线将所有顶点连接起来
a tesseract, some two-dimensional projection of a four-dimensional cube.
这样就得到一个拟四维立方体 就是四维立方体的某种二维投影
And so you can do this, but it's not very helpful for
你可以这样做 但是对可视化没什么帮助
visualization, because you've got all these different directions that are being
因为多个方向都是投影到同一二维图面中
projected into a two-dimensional image, and after three dimensions, we're just
在三维之后 我们并不习惯于认知
not used to perceiving the world in four or higher dimensions, and so we just have
四维或者更高维度的世界
difficulty perceiving four-dimensional or higher data being projected that way.
所以我们对理解四维或者更高维的物体投影 到二维平面上有很大认知障碍
If I have a scatter plot, for example, I can pretty readily see x and
比如说 我有一个散点图 我可以很容易看出
y encoded in the positional Cartesian coordinates of x and y here.
x 和 y 在笛卡尔坐标系中的位置
If I had a z coordinate that's being projected,
如果再加入一条 z 坐标轴
z is being foreshortened as it's being projected here, and
z 轴被缩短了 以使它看起来是一条投影坐标轴
I've gotta mentally remember that z is some combination of horizontal and
我必须提醒自己注意 z 轴 是水平和垂直坐标轴的组合
vertical that's different than the horizontal x or the vertical y axis.
它既不是水平轴 x 也不是垂直轴 y
So you can draw these hints that are basically similar to a shadow,
所以你可以画一些类似投影的辅助线
where I'm indicating, with these dashed lines,
在这里我用的是虚线
what the coordinates of this green dot are in three dimensions,
用这些虚线来表示绿点所在的 三维坐标系中的坐标值
because it lacks other visual cues of where it is in three dimensions.
这样做是因为我们没有视觉辅助 来指示它们在三维坐标中的位置
If you try to do this in four dimensions,
如果你试图在四维系统中做同样的事情
then it becomes a nightmare to manage all those dimensions.
那么就会想噩梦一样难以控制这些维度
So there's a better technique for doing this called parallel coordinates that
幸好我们有更好的方法 叫做平行坐标系
Al Inselberg demonstrated to me back in the early 90s,
Al Inselberg在90年代初给我展示过
when they were first invented, and I was quite blown away by his demonstration, and
那时候这种方法刚发明 我看完之后当时就震惊了
I'll try to reproduce it here.
现在我给你们还原一下啊
So on parallel coordinates, we're going to take the Cartesian coordinates.
在平行坐标系中 我们采用笛卡尔坐标
We have a horizontal x-axis and a vertical y-axis, and
我们有水平的 x 轴和垂直的 y 轴
we're going to take these axes and we're going to
然后我们要把这些坐标轴
make them parallel instead of orthogonal, at right angles, as they usually are.
扭成平行的 而像平时那样垂直的 成直角的
So I'm going to take the x-axis, I'm going to put it here, and
现在我要把 x 坐标轴移动到这里
I'm going to take the y-axis and I'm going to put it here.
现在移动 y 轴到这里
And so I'll label this axis x and this axis y.
我同样给这两个坐标轴命名为 x 和 y
So now the two axes are not orthogonal.
那么现在这两条坐标轴不是垂直的了
They're parallel to each other and they don't extend from the same origin.
它们彼此平行 没有相交
So the origin here is horizontally at the bottom and
那么原点是在坐标轴的底部
increasing x goes up this axis, increasing y goes up this axis.
x 值增加就沿 x 轴往上走 y 值增加就沿 y 轴向上走
So now I've got the data points, and I need to figure out where these data points
那么现在看我们的数据点 我要把这些数据点放在什么位置呢
occur, so if I take the y-coordinates of each data point,
那如果我拿到所有数据点的 y 坐标值
I can map each point onto its corresponding position on the y-axis.
我可以将这些点绘制在相应的 y 坐标上
I'm just basically dragging them across horizontally, because their position in y
我可以将这些点水平的拖拽到 y 轴上 因为新的 y 轴和原有的 y 轴同样方向
in this chart corresponds to their height along this y-axis.
在这个图表里 点的位置等同于 在原图中 y 轴上的高度
If I want to do the same for
我现在要对 x 轴做同样的操作
the x-axis, I'm going to basically take the x position of each point, and then I'm
我要把每个点在原来的 x 轴的位置
going to drag it to the corresponding x position on this vertical x-axis, so
转化为垂直的 x 轴上的相应位置
the horizontal length here corresponds to the vertical length here, and
所以左图中水平的长度就是 右图中垂直的高度
so blue and red are at the same horizontal x coordinate, and so
因为蓝点和红点有相同的水平 x 坐标
they overlap each other on the x-axis.
所以它们在垂直的 x 坐标上重合
And in green is a little bit farther to the right, so
绿点在它们右边一点点
it's going to be a little bit higher on the parallel x-axis.
所以在垂直的 x 轴上比红蓝两点要高一些
Yellow is a little bit farther to the right so
黄点又再靠右边一些
it's going to be a little bit higher.
所以它在这边就走的更高一点
And then this blue green color dot is the farthest right so
蓝绿点在最右端
it'll be the highest on the x-axis.
所以它在 x 轴上的位置最高
So now I've got this one set of points that's now appearing as two
我原来坐标系中的一组点现在看起来
sets of points, and I've got a correspondence between color,
成了两组点 这两组点由颜色联系
and color's a good perceptual indicator of category, but
颜色可以很好用来区别不同的类别
it's very difficult to perceive what's going on here.
但是我们很难理解这个图表的含义
So what we're going to do is, instead of displaying these as points on the axis,
那么我们将这么作 取代将这些点画在坐标轴上
I'm going to connect these points with lines, and
而是要将它们连成线
I'm going to delete the original points, and
我现在要将这些点删去
now we get this nice duality between points in the coordinate system,
现在我们在这个坐标系的点之间 获得了优美的二元线段
here, and lines in the coordinate system, here.
就是在坐标系中的这些 和这些线
So, this orange point, here, has an x-coordinate and a y-coordinate.
所以这个橙色的点 具有x值和y值
It corresponds to this line connecting its x-coordinate to its y-coordinate.
对应于这条连 代表了它的x值和y值
And so each one of these five points in the Cartesian x y coordinate
所以在这个笛卡尔坐标系中 五个点中的每一个点
system corresponds to a line in the parallel x y coordinate system here.
与在平行坐标系中的每一条线 是对应的
Some other features are collinearity, so if these three points lie along
一些其他的特性有共线性 所以如果这三个点
the same line, then you get this nice convergence in parallel coordinates.
在同一条线上 那么在平行坐标系它们会共有一交点
And so you can see some co-linearity that happens, because lines in parallel
所以在这里你可看到共线性存在 即在平行坐标中的线
coordinates, corresponding to points in Cartesian coordinates that are collinear,
若其对应的笛卡尔坐标系中的点具有共线性
will basically converge in a point in the parallel coordinate system.
那么那些在平行坐标系中的线 必会在某同一点相交
So you can add extra dimensions.
所以你可以增加另外的维度
If I add a z-axis here, I'd have to add all sorts of three-dimensional queues to
如果我在这里增加一z轴 那么需要增加各种三维的辅助标识
these data points to figure out where they are in three dimensions.
才可以把这些数据点在三维中的位置表示出来
In parallel coordinates, I just add a z-axis here.
在平行坐标系里 我只是在这里增加了个z轴
And then I can connect the z-coordinates to the y-coordinates,
之后我能将z轴连到y轴上
and follow this line from its x-coordinate to its y-coordinate to its z-coordinate.
然后就能跟随这条线 从它的x轴 到y轴 到z轴
And if I add a fourth w-axis.
之后如果我增加第四条w轴
It's actually easy to add a fourth axis here.
在这里增加第四条轴 这实际上很简单
And in fact, all of these points may be collinear in the z w coordinate system,
事实上 所有的这些点可能 在z和w轴上是共线性的
and you can see because these lines are kind of converging to the same point.
你可看到这些线趋于收敛于同一点
The point that they converge to doesn't necessarily have to be between the axes.
他们收敛的点并不一定要在坐标轴之间
But there are some ways of helping a person to see these points.
但是这里有一些方法 来帮助一个人看到这些点
And so these parallel coordinates are really useful for high-dimensional data.
所以这种平行坐标系在高维数据中 是十分有用的
And you get this correspondence of being able to follow these lines through
所以你能够通过这些线来连接
the various coordinates and have them correspond to points here, and
不同的坐标系 并与点相对应
it's easier to see some relationships.
这也能更加容易的看到一些关系
There could be correspondences between the w-axis and the y-axis, and
在w轴和y轴也可能存在对应关系
we wouldn't see those unless we also had lines from these points on
并且我们不会看到这种对应性 除非我们将这些在
the w-axis to the points on the y-axis, and so you get a bit of a combinatorial
w轴和y轴上对应的点连起来
nightmare when you try to connect every axis to every other axis.
这样当将每一条坐标轴和另外的连起来时 就会造成一个相当复杂的组合
So there's some decision making that needs to happen if you're going to show
所以当你若需展示不同坐标的对应关系
correspondences between axes,
那就需要决定
to choose to have those axes next to each other in the parallel coordinates system.
将那些坐标轴临近放在一起
So parallel coordinates take the orthogonal axes of the Cartesian
所以平行坐标轴将笛卡尔坐标系的正交轴 转换为平行轴
coordinate system and they lay them out in parallel, and you can have any number of
这样你可以有任意数量的平行轴
these parallel coordinate axes laid next to each other, and you can start to
相邻摆放
perceive higher dimensional data using these parallel coordinates.
这样 你就可以借助平行坐标轴 来感知更高维度的数据
Some of the problems of parallel coordinates are the fact that you're only
平行坐标轴的一些问题在于
seeing the pairwise relationship between the axes, but they can be very useful for
你只能看到坐标轴的成对关系
finding certain features in your data, for example, collinearity.
但是它能对于观察到数据的的某些性质非常有效 例如 共线性
[MUSIC]
[背景音乐] 翻译: RyukaSuu |审阅: 19waa Coursera Global Translator Community